Good morning. Today's דף daf is פ"ז ע"ב, Peh Zayin Amud Beis,
פ"ח ע"א. Peh Ches Amud Alef. We're almost, almost only an עמוד
amud behind. We're almost on פ"ז ע"ב Peh Zayin Amud Beis at
least. We pick up on פ"ז ע"א, Peh Zayin Amud Alef, about
five lines down in the wide lines, האומר אחטא ואשוב. ha'omer echta
ve'ashuv. Okay, so continuing on the משנה, Mishna, and we just had
a whole long passage about the power of תשובה teshuva and also
a certain element of צדיק ורע לו רשע וטוב לו, tzaddik vera
lo rasha vetov lo, how the divine accounting works out and so
on. These are very important discussions also about how people deal with
past sins and should they be going back to them and doing
תשובה teshuva on them. Should they be doing תשובה teshuva in public
or in private? A lot of very important discussions about the context
in which תשובה teshuva is done. So now we continue with the
משנה: Mishna: האומר אחטא ואשוב, אחטא ואשוב. ha'omer echta ve'ashuv, echta ve'ashuv.
Somebody says I'll sin and do תשובה, teshuva, I'll sin and do
תשובה, teshuva, it says אין מספיקין בידו לעשות תשובה. ein maspikin beyado
la'asos teshuva. He is not given an opportunity to do תשובה, teshuva,
which again does not mean that the תשובה teshuva is not accepted,
but that his, you know again, there's this underlying theme that תשובה
teshuva will always be accepted, but the opportunities are not made available
for such a person. So the גמרא Gemara says למה לי למימר
אחטא ואשוב, אחטא ואשוב? lama li lemimar echta ve'ashuv, echta ve'ashuv? Why
does it say it twice? תרי זימני? trei zimnei? כדרב הונא אמר
רב, ked'Rav Huna amar Rav, like רב הונא אמר רב, Rav Huna
amar Rav, דאמר רב הונא אמר רב, de'amar Rav Huna amar Rav,
כיון שעבר אדם עבירה ושנה בה הותרה לו. keivan she'avar adam aveira
veshana bah hutra lo. The person does an עבירה aveira and repeats
it, it becomes permissible to him. הותרה לו? hutra lo? Permissible to
him? סלקא דעתך? salka da'atach? Do you really mean that? אלא נעשית
לו כהיתר. ela na'asis lo keheter. No, it means from his perspective,
now it's permissible. We're so good at rationalizing our behavior that once
we've done it two times, it's like it's permissible. And רב ישראל
סלנט Rav Yisrael Salant had the great line, he says and when
you do it three times it's become a מצוה mitzvah already.
So anyway, so the האומר אחטא ואשוב ha'omer echta ve'ashuv here is
sort of saying, but it's interesting because, you know, it, I think
the פשט pshat of it is that it's reading the משנה Mishna
אין מספיקין בידו לעשות תשובה ein maspikin beyado la'asos teshuva not like
divine, from some divine control he's prevented from doing תשובה, teshuva, but
essentially it's reading it psychologically. You know, אחטא ואשוב, אחטא ואשוב echta
ve'ashuv, echta ve'ashuv is reading the significance is that you've reinforced this
behavior in your own mind and you've now rationalized it and it's
become like היתר. heter. And presumably, and that's why אין מספיקין בידו
לעשות תשובה, ein maspikin beyado la'asos teshuva, that's why it's not going
to be easy. That's the natural consequence, how are you supposed to
do תשובה teshuva now that you've completely rationalized the behavior and it's
become to you to be like היתר? heter? Although the irony is,
is that then it's really just about doing an עבירה aveira twice,
it's not about saying אחטא ואשוב echta ve'ashuv twice. If you're saying
אחטא ואשוב echta ve'ashuv but maybe the point that is revealing the
fact that you're rationalizing what you're doing. I mean if you just
sin twice, you could sin twice without rationalizing it and feel guilty
about it. But if you're sinning and saying I'll do תשובה, teshuva,
you're already figuring out a way why what you're doing is not
so bad and how you'll work it all out. But it is
interesting that rather than reading it as a type of מדה כנגד
מדה, midah keneged midah, you're trying to rely on the תשובה teshuva
to help you sin. The normal way this is taught is you're
using the תשובה teshuva to help you sin and therefore you're not
given the opportunity to use, to actually avail yourself of this תשובה.
teshuva. But this is I think reading it less that way and
more just reading if you're rationalizing your behavior, the reality is it's
going to be very hard for you to do תשובה. teshuva. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara continues:
אחטא ויום הכיפורים מכפר, אין יום הכיפורים מכפר. echta veYom HaKippurim mechaper,
ein Yom HaKippurim mechaper. If you say I'll sin and יום הכיפורים
Yom HaKippurim will atone, then יום הכיפורים Yom HaKippurim will not atone.
That is much more מדה כנגד מדה midah keneged midah because whether
יום הכיפורים Yom HaKippurim atones or not is somehow, you know, the
metaphysical power of יום הכיפורים. Yom HaKippurim. That's more about what God
does, not about your actual actions of תשובה. teshuva. So the גמרא
Gemara says: לימא מתניתין דלא כרבי. leima matnisin d'lo ke-Rabbi. Let's say
our משנה Mishna is not like רבי. Rabbi. דתניא, detanya, רבי אומר,
Rabbi omer, על כל עבירות שבתורה בין עשה תשובה בין לא עשה
תשובה יום הכיפורים מכפר, al kol aveiros shebaTorah bein asa teshuva bein
lo asa teshuva Yom HaKippurim mechaper, that whether you've done תשובה teshuva
or not יום הכיפורים Yom HaKippurim is מכפר mechaper because the גמרא
Gemara assumes that if יום הכיפורים Yom HaKippurim isn't going to work,
it's because what's lacking is the תשובה. teshuva. But according to רבי
Rabbi who doesn't need תשובה, teshuva, then presumably even with this problem
it should work. So the גמרא Gemara writes, so it's interesting again
the גמרא's Gemara's desire to read this problem here, this issue here
not as a מדה כנגד מדה midah keneged midah but as some
obstacle in your תשובה. teshuva. And the גמרא Gemara answer is: אפילו
תימא רבי. afilu teima Rabbi. No, even according to רבי Rabbi that
יום הכיפורים Yom HaKippurim works by itself, אגב שאני. agav shani. If
you try to use יום הכיפורים Yom HaKippurim to, you know, to
help you sin, then it's not going to work. That would exclude
the efficacy of יום הכיפורים Yom HaKippurim since that is what basically
supported you in your, psychologically in your sinning. עבירות שבין אדם למקום.
aveiros shebein adam laMakom. Now the sins that you do between man
and God יום הכיפורים Yom HaKippurim works, but between one person and
another you need to appease your friend. רמי ליה רב יוסף בר
חבו ליה לרבי אבהו. rami lei Rav Yosef bar Chavo lei le-Rabbi
Abbahu. רב יוסף בר חבו Rav Yosef bar Chavo challenged רבי אבהו.
Rabbi Abbahu. What? What did he do?
Challenge, like רמי rami means to show a contradiction of פסוקים, psukim,
not challenge a statement he had made, show a contradiction of פסוקים,
psukim, that's what רמי rami means, to throw two verses together. עבירות
שבין אדם לחבירו אין יום הכיפורים מכפר. aveiros shebein adam lachaveiro ein
Yom HaKippurim mechaper. Is that really true? that between man and his
friend יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* does not work, does not
work until you appease? וכתיב *U'khtiv* אם יחטא איש לאיש ופללו אלהים
*im yechete ish l'ish u'pilelo Elokim*. So if a person sins to
another person then ופללו *pilelo*, which is a as the JPS translation
has it, meaning of Hebrew uncertain.
But ופללו *pilelo* could mean like to judge, God will judge it,
but by the context, and this is presumably why he's asking, by
the context it means this is with עלי *Eli* remonstrating his sons
for their sins and they're saying look, if a person sins to
God, God will atone, but if you sin to your fellow man,
who will atone? So the atone here seems to be forgive, right,
which actually seems to be saying the opposite, which we're on... I'm
sorry, I'm sorry, I said it the wrong way. If a person
sins against a person, God will atone, but if you sin against
God, who's going to atone? So it sounds from the context that
what he's talking about is forgive. If you sin to your fellow
man, God will forgive it, but if you're sinning to God, who's
going to forgive it? And he's trying to give him מוסר *mussar*
about how terrible the sin is and why they have to do
תשובה teshuva *teshuvah*. So the word ופללו *pilelo* there, I don't know,
but in the context it seems to mean forgive, to weigh, to
judge, to judge in the context of forgiving, and there the simple
sense of the verse is the exact opposite of our משנה *Mishnah*,
that God will forgive sins between people but not done directly to
God. So of course what it could mean done to God in
a sense of like חילול השם *chillul Hashem*, but okay. So anyway
here's the problem: אם יחטא איש לאיש ופללו אלהים *im yechete ish
l'ish u'pilelo Elokim*. So look, it seems like God does forgive those
sins. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no, מאן אלהים דיינא *man
Elokim dayana*. It doesn't mean God, it means judges, and presumably then
reading the word ופללו *pilelo* means that judges will judge it. If
you sin against your neighbor, it'll be brought to the court, okay.
So then let's take a look. אי הכי אימא סיפא *ei hachi
eima seifa*, so then how does the end of the verse work?
ואם לה' יחטא איש *ve'im l'Hashem yechete ish*, if he sins against
God, מי יתפלל לו *mi yitpallel lo*? So what does that mean,
who will... if the word ופללו *pilelo* here means to judge, who
will judge him? What do you mean who will judge him? God
will judge him. So הכי קאמר *hachi ka'amar*: אם יחטא איש לאיש
ופללו *im yechete ish l'ish u'pilelo*... so now we're going back to
the earlier reading that ופללו *pilelo* means to forgive. If a person
sins against another person, God will ופללו *u'pilelo* dash אלהים ימחול *Elokim
yimchol*, God will forgive him. Okay. So meaning, I'm sorry, so ופללו
*u'pilelo* or ימחול לו *yimchol lo*... אם יחטא איש לאיש ופללו *im
yechete ish l'ish u'pilelo* dash אלהים ימחול *Elokim yimchol*. Right, thank you.
אם יחטא איש לאיש ופללו *im yechete ish l'ish u'pilelo* dash mean
ופללו *u'pilelo* then אלהים ימחול *Elokim yimchol*.
Oh, and the person is ופללו *u'pilelo*, meaning
the other person forgives him. Is that how it's reading it? Something
like if you sin to another person and that person forgives you,
then אלהים ימחול *Elokim yimchol*, then God will forgive you. ואם לה'
יחטא איש *ve'im l'Hashem yechete ish*, and but if you sin to
God, מי יתפלל בעדו *mi yitpallel ba'ado*, who will atone for you
or you know forgive you? תשובה teshuva. ומעשים טובים *teshuvah u'ma'asim tovim*,
then your תשובה teshuva, *teshuvah* will forgive you. So it's a pretty
convoluted read of the verse,
but basically it's saying not that not that you won't be forgiven
if you sin to God, actually if you sin to God you
will be forgiven if you do תשובה teshuva. *teshuvah*. But if you
sin to another person, you'll be forgiven once the person forgives you.
So anyway, it's a hard read of the verse. The simple read
of the verse is actually quite the opposite of the משנה *Mishnah*,
but nevertheless we are claiming that it works with the sense of
the משנה *Mishnah*. אמר amar, רבי Rabbi. יצחק *Amar Rabbi Yitzchak*, says
רבי Rabbi's יצחק *Rabbi Yitzchak*: כל המקניט את חבירו אפילו בדברים צריך
לפייסו *kol hamaknit es chaveiro afilu bidvarim tzarich l'fayeso*. Anybody who upsets
his friend, who does wrong to his friend, even with words, has
to appease him. שנאמר she-ne'emar *Shene'emar*, alright, בני אם ערבת לרעך *beni
im aravta l're'echa*, my son, if you have gone into like gone
into league you know with your friend, תקעת לזר כפיך *takata l'zar
kapecha*, stuck out to a stranger your hand, like shaking your hands
with somebody, נוקשת באמרי פיך *nokashta b'imrei picha*, and you have tripped
or you know done wrong with the words of your mouth, עשה
זאת אפוא בני והנצל *aseh zos efo beni v'hinatzel*, do this my
son and be saved, כי באת בכף רעך *ki vasa b'chaf re'echa*,
if you have come again with you know in the handshake of
your friend to do some dastardly deed, לך התרפס ורהב רעך *lech
hitrapes u'rehav re'echa*. Go התרפס *hitrapes* and רהב רעך *rehav re'echa*. What
does that mean? So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is going to explain.
אם ממון יש בידך *im mamon yesh b'yadcha*, so if what you've
done is basically... now it might be reading בכף רעך *b'chaf re'echa*
like your friend's hand, like you've taken money out of his hand.
The simple sense of the verse probably means you've done a handshake
in order to do some dastardly deed.
But anyway, what was רהב רעך *rehav re'echa*?
We are going to see. If you have anyway if you have
money, אם ממון יש בידך *im mamon yesh b'yadcha*, then התרפס *hitrapes*
התר לו פיסת יד *hatter lo pisas yad*. So it's a wordplay
on the word התרפס *hitrapes*, open up the palm of your hand,
give the money back. ואם לאו *ve'im lav*, and if it's not
with money but you've just done like נוקשת באמרי פיך *nokashta b'imrei
picha*, done stuff wrong with the words of your mouth, so התרפס
ורהב רעך *hitrapes u'rehav re'echa* is read הרבה עליו רעים *harbe alav
re'im*, from רהב *rahav* הרבה *harbe*, הרבה עליו רעים *harbe alav re'im*,
have a lot of friends come and appease him on your behalf
and have him forgive you. So you see even if in a
way, if you take money it's easy. to return money maybe, but
if you actually hurt him with your words, you know that might
actually be even more demanding and go and get friends together, his
friends, and try to appease him. אמר רב Rav חסדא וצריך לפייסו
בשלוש שורות u-tzarikh le-fayeso be-shalosh shurot this is again some people might
be familiar with this. This is brought down להלכה. le-halakha. When you
go to appease your friend that you've done wrong to him, you
have to bring three rows of friends, you know, to help try
to
persuade him, presumably if he doesn't just want to forgive you more
easily. שלוש שורות של שלושה בני אדם shalosh shurot shel shlosha bnei
adam three rows of three people each, שנאמר ישור על אנשים she-ne'emar
yashur al anashim so you shall make a row of on people.
So basically a row is at least three people. ויאמר חטאתי va-yomer
hatati and you shall say I’ve sinned וישר העויתי ve-yashar he'eveti and
I have perverted what is straight ולא שווה לי ve-lo shava li
and it has not been any good for me. So again three
different statements, right? חטאתי, hatati, ישר העויתי, ve-yashar he'eveti, ולא שווה לי,
ve-lo shava li, so and three times with a row of friends.
So you have to be so much trying to win him over
that you would have to come to him back three times, each
time bringing a group of friends to try to persuade him to
make up with you. Does that make a minyan? I didn't think
about that. That's an interesting
point. Three times three plus him makes a minyan. We're going to
mention a minyan in a minute. So that's a very good point.
אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא Amar Rabbi Yosi berabi Hanina כל המבקש
מטות מחברו kol ha-mevakesh matot me-havero matot is forgiveness במטו מינך be-matu
minakh the famous say with, you know, with your leave, with your
forgiveness. Pardon me, pardon me, with your pardon. Anybody who requests forgiveness
from his friend אל יבקש ממנו יותר משלוש פעמים. al yivakesh mimeno
yoter mi-shalosh pe'amim. On the other side, you don't have to continue
to debase yourself so much. If it's not working three times, you've
done your duty. שנאמר as the verse says אנא שא נא ana
sa na please, apparently is one. שא נא sa na is two.
And three times it says please. ועתה שא נא ve-ata sa na
is three times. So more than that you do not have to
debase yourself.
So אנא ana is one, שא נא
sa na is two, ועתה שא נא ve-ata sa na is three.
ואם מת ve-im met
now,
let's say the person died and you did not achieve forgiveness. Maybe
you didn't get around to doing the three times or you did
the three times and we're not asking you to do any more,
but there's still a reality that you've sinned and it hasn't been
forgiven. So what do you do? מביא עשרה בני אדם ומעמידן על
קברו. mevi asara bnei adam u-ma’amidan al kivro. Here you do get
the minyan. You get ten people and you stand on his and
you have them stand by his grave
ואומר חטאתי לה׳ אלוהי ישראל ולפלוני שחבלתי בו. ve-omer hatati la-Hashem Elohei
Yisrael u-lifloni she-havalti bo. I sinned to God and to this person
that I did injury to him. And presumably now, you know, since
the person isn't around to say no and you're doing so, somehow
it can sort of represent his side. You know, it's not exactly
clear what this ritual is supposed to do, but somehow this minyan
either it's the public confession of it, you know, is somehow suffices
in itself when there's nothing left to be done, or somehow these
ten people as a representative of the ציבור tzibbur also represent his
interest on the other side.
That's if he died,
that's if he was alive. That's if he did not get to
forgive you while he was alive.
No, or if he didn't get to do the three. I mean,
if he did
it once, you're not going to- you don't have to- that's an
interesting question. If you did it three times and he still said
no, are you still required to do this? You're not required to
more debase yourself, but, you know, to him. But maybe still the
accounts haven't been even, you know. So, okay. רבי ירמיה הוה ליה
מילתא לרבי אבא בהדיה. Rabbi Yirmiya hava leh milta le-Rabbi Abba behadeih.
Now we get some I think very moving stories about how people,
you know, reconciled with other people, or attempted to reconcile. רבי ירמיה
הוה ליה מילתא לרבי אבא בהדיה. Rabbi Yirmiya hava leh milta le-Rabbi
Abba behadeih. So it's again interesting just the terminology used. Rabbi Abba
had a- had, you know, had some- Rabbi Yirmiya had offended Rabbi
Abba. So the way it describes it is, there was a matter
of Rabbi Yirmiya that Rabbi Abba had with it. Meaning Rabbi Abba
had some type of a complaint, you know, but some type of
a- of offense that was done to him by Rabbi Yirmiya. So
he had this matter being held by him, this problem. אזל יתיב
אדשא דרבי אבא. Azal yativ adasha de-Rabbi Abba. So Rabbi Yirmiya went
and he sat by the door of Rabbi Abba. בהדי דשדיא אמתא
מיא Bahadi de-shadya amta maya and he was going there, he was
going to ask forgiveness, he was waiting to get in, and while
he was waiting, his- the maidservant threw water, you know, cleaning the
house and threw out the water from the- the dirty water, maybe
even the bathroom water.
מיא מטו זריפי דמיא ארישא. Maya matu zarifi de-maya areisha. So some
of the drops of water hit his head that he was sitting
there on the doorstep waiting to come in. אמר עשיתוני כאשפה. Amar
asituni ke-ashpa. So now I've become like a garbage dump. So maybe
that's like my כפרה. kapara.
קרא
אנפשיה Kara anafsheih he called on himself מאשפות ירים אביון. me-ashpot yarim
evyon. And again this interesting, God raises- lifts up from the garbage
dumps the poor. So again I've so debased myself, which is interesting
if you think in the context of יום כיפור Yom Kippur and
about self-affliction ועניתם את נפשותיכם, ve-initem et nafshoteichem, is the idea that
you have suffered and had these bad things done to you itself
a
כפרה? kapara? Also, you know, or we've also been alluding to this
idea... that the process of asking for forgiveness to some degree requires
a certain degree of self-abasement. So here he's making himself, he is
like this is a very
like real-world way of being treated like garbage. Being treated like garbage
he had ואשפות ירים אביון ve'ashpos yarim evyon but so sometimes maybe
the process, you know, it's hard to ask for forgiveness. You have
to sort of, you know, make yourself more humble and, you know,
and there's that idea of, you know, feeling feeling bad about it
about yourself and feeling like garbage and so here this was what
came as part of the process, yes.
Instead of being angry, he had the awareness like this was appropriate.
Right, right, that's a good point too. Right, he didn't get angry.
He felt that this was like some degree appropriate. Although you don't
know עשוני asuni they've made me, again is there a little sense
of like it's gotten this bad like a little a little subtext
of complaint. Anyway שמע רבי אבא, Shama Rabi Abba, רבי אבא Rabi
Abba heard ונפק לאפיה venafak le'apeih and went to greet him. אמר
ליה השתא צריכנא למיפק אדעתך amar leih hashta tzerichna lemeifak adateich
now I have to go ahead and like you know and make
you you know appease you that this is how you were you
know you were treated even inadvertently. למיפק lemeifak to make you go
out of your mind not go out of your mind but like
meaning to leave your your anger. Right. So again so it does
seem he was you know got was upset that that's what happened.
דכתיב לך התרפס ורהב רעיך. dechativ lech hisrapes urahav reiecha. Okay, so
again it's quite fascinating the symbolism of it but his sense that
you know was a little bit too much. רב זירא Rav Zeira
which again fits into the previous discussion about not you know about
limiting the degree of debasement. רבי זירא Rabi Zeira כי הוה ליה
מילתא בהדי אינש ki hava leih milsa bahadi inash now
when רבי זירא Rabi Zeira had a complaint against people meaning somebody
had done something wrong to him הוה חליף ותני לקמיה hava chalif
vesani lekameih he would go out of his way once and multiple
times תני sani like a second time to like you know bump
into him on the street, make himself you know present himself to
him but not like obviously like you know make himself bump into
him on the street כי היכי דנייתי וניפוק ליה מדעתיה ki heichi
denaysi venafak leih mada'ateih so the person should come and again the
phrase ניפוק ליה מדעתיה neifak leih mada'ateih הוציא לו מדעתו hotzi lo
mada'ato come to get him out of his state of mind meaning
appease him. So what it's the point is that on the one
hand he's not going for you know it's not like the חפץ
חיים Chafetz Chaim stories where he's running after him saying אני מוחל
אני מוחל ani mochel ani mochel but he does want that the
person should ask forgiveness, maybe he himself feels offended and wants to
be asked forgiveness, maybe it's appropriate for the person's own תשובה teshuva
process that the person should ask but you also realize that sometimes
the hardest thing is to just actually get not not say well
yes but first get up the strength to actually go and talk
to the person, right you know but you know once you're in
the conversation maybe sometimes you're able to do it so he actually
did not sort of waive the need for the person to ask
for forgiveness but made bumped into him to make it more easy
for the person to have that opportunity, did it you know didn't
wait for the person to come to him. So sort of as
we say met him halfway. So that's what he would do. רב
Rav הוה ליה מילתא בהדי ההוא טבחא Rav hava leih milsa bahadi
hahu tavcha רב Rav. had a certain issue against a certain butcher
that the butcher had done something offensive to רב. Rav. לא אתא
לקמיה lo asa lekameih and the butcher never came to say anything
to רב. Rav So again from the previous story we learn well
maybe you do the guy a favor maybe you'll go out of
your way and bump into him.
So במעלי יומא דכפורי bemalei yoma dekippurei אמר איהו amar ihu so
ערב יום כיפור Erev Yom Kippur רב Rav said איזיל אנא לפיוסיה
ליה eizel ana le'piyusei leih
so I will go to
you know to make peace with him meaning so רב Rav, was
going to actually go and since the butcher didn't come to רב,
Rav רב Rav was going to the butcher. פגע ביה רב הונא
paga beih Rav Huna so רב הונא Rav Huna bumped into him.
אמר ליה להיכא קא אזיל מר amar leih leheicha ka azil mar
where's the master going? אמר ליה לפיוסיה לפלניא amar leih le'piyusei leplanya
so to appease so and so. It's actually interesting because it sounds
like רב Rav. is the one that needs to needs to appease
the butcher although again it's interesting because it sounded like the butcher
was the one that had done something wrong to רב. Rav Let
the other story continue. אמר איזיל אבא למיקטל נפשא amar eizel Abba
lemiktal nafsha so so he says אבא Abba which apparently was רב's
Rav, actual name is going to kill someone. So he did not
trust רב, Rav he knew רב's Rav nature and that if רב
Rav that it was not going to end well even though רב
Rav. was trying to be the one to make peace this is
רב. Rav Himself exactly. אזל וקם עילויה azal vekam ilaveih so he
went and he stood by him הוה יתיב וקא פלי רישא hava
yasiv veka pali reisha so he was going to again unless I'm
reading this wrong and it's the butcher that was going to רב
Rav but it doesn't make sense because רב Rav is coming and
the butcher was in the middle of a chopping up the head
of an animal. דלי עיניה וחזיה dali eineih vechazeih
yeah exactly he lifted up his eyes and and the butcher lifted
up his eyes and he saw רב Rav coming and he said
אמר ליה אבא את amar leih Abba at you who you're אבא
Abba again which is רב's Rav like actual name which is not
a respectful name of calling רב Rav right? So זיל לית לי
מילתא בהדך zil leis li milsa bahadach go get out of here
I don't want to have anything to do with you. ובהדי דקא
פלי רישא vehadai deka pali reisha and then he continued chopping this
head. of this animal, אשתמיט גרמא, ishtamit garma, a bone flew out
of the animal, ומחיה בקוועיה, umachyei bikveih, and hit him, the butcher,
in the forehead, דקטליה, dekatleh, and killed him. So we actually see
that רב Rav succeeded in not intentionally, but רב Rav. actually through
this encounter, it wound up that he did die. It's actually quite
interesting because because wait, the next word in the גמרא Gemara is
רב. Rav So you could have read it וקטליה רב. v'katleh Rav.
I don't know if that was intentional or not but that was
what it says his name said, right? He said רב Rav is
going, אבא Abba is going to kill someone. So anyway, so here
you see that sometimes it didn't exactly work out. He was trying
to make up with him but look, you know, I remember a
very powerful thing that was written by this colleague of mine אריה
בן דוד Ariye Ben David or whatever in Israel and you know
I remember being very moved that he wrote a powerful piece once
in the עשרת ימי תשובה Aseret Yimei Teshuva about how he had
this like long-standing
fight with his neighbor. Of course, as will often happen in these
cases, each side thinks that they're wronged and each side thinks that
the other one has done a terrible thing to them. And he
decided he was going to be the bigger person and so he
went like ערב יום כיפור Erev Yom Kippur he went and apologized
and make up this and that, took responsibility, and the guy basically
just slammed the door in his face. You know, and refused to
accept it, and those are like the really hard times where you
think you're being the big person, the way like רב Rav felt
he was offended but he says I'm going to go make up
with him and nevertheless, now of course in this story the guy
got payback for being so
intransigent but nevertheless that's sometimes the sad reality, it doesn't always work
out. You were going to say something Seth?
I was just going to say I think maybe that's part of
the story about how important it is if somebody comes to you
to accept their apology.
Oh, because look what will happen if you don't. And if we
want to again use it sort of more metaphorically, your anger, your
resistance in the end is going to wind up coming back and
hurting you. That's a very nice point. Okay.
רב הוה פסיק סידרא קמי דרבי. Rav hava pasik sidra kamei d'Rabbi.
רב Rav was teaching the סדרא, sidra, the פרשה parsha of the
פרשת
השבוע, Parshat Hashavua, some פסוקים pesukim in תנ"ך. Tanakh. Okay, so he
was giving a תנ"ך שיעור Tanakh shiur in front of
רבי. Rebbi. אתא, ata, he came. Who came? רבי חייא. Rabbi Hiyya.
So
הדר לרישא. hadar l'reisha. So he went back to the beginning. He
said okay we have a new person
here let's start back again from the beginning of the פרק. perek.
So אתא בר קפרא. ata Bar Kappara. בר קפרא Bar Kappara came.
הדר לרישא. hadar l'reisha. So and then again start again from the
beginning. אתא רבי שמעון דרבי. ata Rabbi Shimon d'Rabbi. רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, רבי Rebbi son, came. הדר לרישא. hadar l'reisha. Back to the
beginning. אתא רבי חנינא בר חמא. ata Rabbi Hanina bar Hama. רבי
חנינא בר חמא Rabbi Hanina bar Hama then showed up. Everybody's coming
so late. So אמר כולי האי נהדר וניזיל? amar kulei hai nedar
v'neizeil? What, so much we have to go back again and again
and again, always start from the beginning? Like next time show up
on time. So לא הדר, lo hadar, he didn't go back. איתפז
רבי חנינא. itpiz Rabbi Hanina. So רבי חנינא Rabbi Hanina was offended.
Everybody else you go back to the beginning, I come you don't
go back to the beginning? So
again it seems here like what רב Rav, did was completely reasonable
and why was רבי חנינא Rabbi Hanina anyway coming so late to
the שיעור? shiur? But anyway nevertheless
רבי חנינא Rabbi Hanina was offended. So אזל רב לגביה תליסר מעלי
יומא דכיפורי. azal Rav lgabei tlasar malei yoma d'kippura. 13 ערב יום
כיפור Erev Yom Kippur רב, Rav by the way, the whole practice
of using ערב יום כיפור Erev Yom Kippur the opportunity to ask
for forgiveness we see already in the time of the גמרא, Gemara
the previous story also was an ערב יום כיפור Erev Yom Kippur
story. 13 ערב יום כיפור erev Yom Kippur רב Rav. went to
ask for forgiveness. ולא איפייס. v'lo ipayas. רבי חנינא Rabbi Hanina refused.
But quite fascinating in both of these stories people are refusing to
make up with רב. Rav? Like again what is it exactly about
רב? Rav, ולא איפייס. v'lo ipayas. He had a temper. רב, Rav
והיכי עביד
הכי?
v'heichi avid
hachi?
Now
how could or how did רב Rav do this 13 times? דאמר
רבי יוסי בר חנינא כל המבקש מטות מחבירו אל יבקש ממנו יותר
משלוש פעמים. d'amar Rabbi Yossi bar Hanina kol hamivakeish matzo meichaveiro al
yivakeish mimenu yoter mishalosh peamim. If you ask forgiveness you should not
just, you don't have to
but presumably it seemed like you shouldn't do it more than three
times. רב שאני, Rav shani, no, רב Rav was different. Actually he
was מחמיר machmir on himself. Okay, so he still wanted to make
everything good. So רבי חנינא היכי עביד הכי? Rabbi Hanina heichi avid
hachi? How did רבי חנינא Rabbi Hanina refuse to forgive him? דאמר
רבא כל המעביר על מדותיו מעבירין לו על כל פשעיו. d'amar Rava
kol hamaavir al midosav maavirin lo al kol peshav. Anybody who's
willing to forego their character traits, meaning to forego bad evils that
were done to them, God will take away the person's sins. So
how could you be so intransigent? אלא רבי חנינא, ella Rabbi Hanina,
so rather than saying רבי חנינא Rabbi Hanina was just that way,
some people just can't get over hurts that are done to them,
here's the explanation of why רבי חנינא Rabbi Hanina did it. רבי
חנינא חלמא חזא ליה לרב דזקפוהו בדיקלא. Rabbi Hanina chelma chaza lei
l'Rav d'zakfuhu b'dikla. רבי חנינא Rabbi Hanina had a dream about רב
Rav that רב Rav was suspended on a palm tree. literally hanged
from a palm tree.
Now we would think that that would be a very bad sign,
but דגמירי d'gamiri we have a tradition דכל דזקפוהו בדיקלא d'kol d'zakfuhu
b'dikla if you have a dream about somebody that's being hanged by
a palm tree, רישא הוה. reisha havei. So that means that that
person's going to be very high up, palm trees are high, so
that person is going to be a head. So he basically had
a dream that רב Rav would be a great leader. And אמר
שמע מינה בעי למעבד רישותא, amar shma mina bei l'me'evad rishuta, you
see that רב Rav is going to want to be like, you
know, have a position of leadership. ולא אפייס v'lo efayeis and therefore
I will refuse to be
appeased. Why? היכי דליזיל heichi d'leizil that רב Rav should leave. Like
who wants to be around somebody that's so, you know, mean to
you? וליגמר אורייתא בבבל v'ligmar oraissa b'Bavel and teach Torah in Bavel.
What does this mean? It means as רש"י Rashi says that רבי
חנינא Rabbi Chanina was next in line to being the head of
the ישיבה. yeshiva. And he had this dream that רב Rav. was
going to be a big guy, you know, the leader. So he
didn't want to be competing with רב. Rav, So he basically figured
alright I'll be mean to רב, Rav רב Rav will leave, he'll
go to בבל, Bavel, let him be the ראש ישיבה rosh yeshiva
in בבל. Bavel. Oh, what? That's a good question. He didn't want
to go to בבל? Bavel? I don't know. Yeah.
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina was already the ראש ישיבה. rosh yeshiva. He
was afraid that if רב Rav takes over, that means his time
is over, in other words he's going to die.
Oh you're right, he said רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina was already the
ראש ישיבה. rosh yeshiva. Thank you. So he didn't want, right, right,
thank you. So רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina was already the ראש ישיבה,
rosh yeshiva, so he didn't want, so if רב Rav is going
to be the ראש ישיבה, rosh yeshiva, that means that he's going
to die. Yes, correct. Thank you. So he didn't want to die,
so that's a little bit more understandable. So he didn't want to
die, so he figured let the dream sort of become true in
בבל, Bavel, not here. Spice thing is funny because this is all
in front of רבי. רבי was still alive, so what does it
mean that רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina was the ראש ישיבה? rosh yeshiva?
I'm not exactly sure. Anyway, okay, so that's why. Otherwise, of course
he would have forgiven him. But this was all to,
you know, so that he should stay ראש ישיבה, rosh yeshiva, he
shouldn't die, רב Rav should go get his, become the big guy
in
בבל. Bavel. Alright. תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, our rabbis taught. Those were
some fascinating stories, now back to הלכה. halacha. מצות וידוי ערב יום
כיפור, mitzvat viduy erev Yom Kippur, the way we do וידוי viduy
by the way, again, fascinating, we've talked about the whole issue of
ritual of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash versus תשובה. Also the ritual
of וידוי, viduy, you know, the power of יום כיפור Yom Kippur
without תשובה, certain things have power as opposed to the interior process.
But even the וידוי, viduy, you know, we just left off these
stories which did not, were not ritualized at all, which were about
asking for forgiveness, genuinely encountering the other person, really, you know, making
things right. But now we get to the issues of וידוי, viduy,
which could be okay, it's between you and God now, it's not
between you and a person, but still it's being ritualized and it's
not just the question about doing תשובה. It's about a particular way
of doing וידוי. viduy. So let's take a look. מצות וידוי, mitzvat
viduy, the way you do the מצוה mitzvah of וידוי, viduy, ערב
יום הכיפורים עם חשכה. erev Yom HaKippurim im chasheicha. First of all
you do it ערב יום כיפור erev Yom Kippur. as it's getting
dark, meaning you do it at מנחה mincha on ערב יום כיפור.
erev Yom Kippur,
I'm sorry, you do it, I missed that, I jumped ahead. You
do it when before it already becomes יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, after
יום כיפור Yom Kippur begins. אבל אמרו חכמים, aval amru chachamim, but
the sages said, יתודה קודם שיאכל וישתה. yisvadeh kodem she'yochal v'yishteh. You
should actually do וידוי viduy before you eat on ערב יום כיפור,
erev Yom Kippur which is מנחה mincha time. שמא תטרף דעתו בסעודה,
shema titoraf da'ato b'seuda,
lest you become like you know you eat so much and then
you go literally your mind gets mixed up, but like you know
who knows you sleep
through, you sleep through כל נדרי, Kol Nidrei, so better to do
וידוי viduy ערב יום כיפור erev Yom Kippur before the סעודה. seuda.
ואף על פי שמתודה קודם שיאכל וישתה, v'af al pi she-misyadeh kodem
she'yochal v'yishteh, even though you did it before, מתודה לאחר שיאכל וישתה.
misyadeh l'achar she'yochal v'yishteh. You do it afterwards, you do it at
night at מעריב, Maariv, שמא יארע דבר קלקלה בסעודה, shema ye'ara d'var
kalkala b'seuda,
maybe you sinned during the meal, you ate too much, you forgot
to make a ברכה, bracha, who knows what you did. ואף על
פי שמתודה ערבית, v'af al pi she-misyadeh arvis, and even if you
did it on יום כיפור Yom Kippur night, מתודה שחרית, misyadeh shacharis,
do it in the morning.
שחרית מתודה במוסף, shacharis misyadeh b'mussaf, במוסף מתודה במנחה, b'mussaf misyadeh b'mincha,
במנחה מתודה בנעילה. b'mincha misyadeh b'neila. Okay, so you have to do
it at all those opportunities. So again it's an interesting question, you
know, how to take, take a step back and say like okay
what really is the point? Meaning, you know, is the point that
maybe I sinned between then and now? It could be, right, and
that's the way it's being framed, which
so really once is enough. You do תשובה plus יום כיפור, Yom
Kippur, once is enough, but you know maybe each time you have
to have this anxiety, maybe I sinned between the last
one. Wait minute, or I wasn't being sincere or something of that.
Now the power of that is on the one hand you could
say that's exactly feeds into the whole like you know OCD type
of mentality that some people have around religion, but maybe and you
know but that seems to be what the גמרא Gemara is framing
it. Oh you better do it ערב יום כיפור erev Yom Kippur
lest you, you know, you know you miss the opportunity on יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. And you did it before the סעודה, seuda, maybe
I forgot to make a ברכה bracha during the סעודה seuda I'll
have to do it again. So it does have that type of
a like this hyper-anxiety, but you know maybe in a way that's
like trying to be underscored as a certain type, well could be,
but as a certain type of like a message, not necessarily for
the whole year. The same way יום כיפור Yom Kippur isn't how
you're supposed to act the whole year, not eat and drink,
whatever, you know, it's once a
since you never know when you die you should always do תשובה
*teshuva* every day, you know, yesterday we were talking about, you know,
the ספרדי *Sephardi* מנהג *minhag* of doing a וידוי viduy. *vidui* on
a daily basis. So at least use this day as an opportunity
to have, height- in a sense of anxiety around sin. Not like
we're supposed to go every single day, you know, with this crazy
thing oh my god maybe I just sinned a second ago, oh
my god maybe I just sinned whatever, but we should probably go
with a high- a higher sense of concern than we tend to
go on an everyday day-to-day basis. So use this as an opportunity
to create that heightened sense of concern or anxiety around it to
a little bit more internalize that value. That would be like one
thing I would suggest. More simple explanation, by the way, is which
is not what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying, I'm not trying
to read this in the words of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, but
you do תשובה *teshuva* before יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* so
you should enter into יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*, you know,
already ready for יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur*, like the כהן
kohen גדול *Kohen Gadol*, right, the whole seven days before you have
the עשרת ימי תשובה *Aseret Yemei Teshuva* and so on. And on
יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur* itself, since the whole day is
a day about forgiveness, then the way you ritualize the day, the
whole point is that we don't have an עבודה *avoda* in the
בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* anymore. What is the ritual that we do
to bring out the character of the day? And by doing תשובה
*teshuva* on an ongoing basis at every sort of שמונה עשרה Shmoneh
Esrei *Shemoneh Esrei* and in face, for us that's what makes defines
the day, right? It's not like oh we well I did my
תשובה *teshuva* last week and I'm just waiting around now to get
כפרה *kappara*. Right, the whole nature of a day is a day
about forgiveness and associated with that is a day of asking for
forgiveness. So it's sort of like on ראש חודש *Rosh Chodesh* you
mention יעלה ויבוא *Ya'aleh V'Yavo* every שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh, *Shemoneh Esrei*
and in, you know, חנוכה *Chanukah* you do על הנסים *Al HaNissim*
in every שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh. *Shemoneh Esrei*. So on יום כיפור
Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur* you do וידוי viduy *vidui* at every opportunity.
It brings it- it's exactly what the character of the day is
about. But again, then the power of the shift from the מקדש
*Mikdash* where the whole character was around the עבודה *avoda*, and here
the character of יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur* is מכפר *mechaper*,
but the way you bring out the character of כפרה *kappara* is
through doing a וידוי viduy. *vidui* again, you know, really sort of,
you know, just reinforces that complete shift. That now כפרה *kappara* is
not through some ritual, כפרה *kappara* is about תשובה *teshuva* and it's
completely that's what's intertwined and becomes the character of the day.
Yeah. Maybe I'm just not remembering, but now we have the concept
of all these davening, was this really discussed you know so much
in this מסכת masechet *masechet*?
No,
nope.
This is- this is all
תוספתא *Tosefta* and הלכה *halacha*. Yep. And this is the whole discussion.
So let's try to see how much if we can finish the
discussion, okay? So now it says like this. והיכן אומרו *v'heichan omro*,
where do you say the וידוי viduy *vidui*? יחיד לאחר תפילתו *Yachid
l'achar tefilaso*, the יחיד *yachid* after שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh *Shemoneh Esrei*.
Which again is a little bit against my point because it's- because
it's not completely embedded in the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh *Shemoneh Esrei*,
but also there's an idea that that's your private וידוי viduy *vidui*.
And the basic idea of a שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh. *Shemoneh Esrei*
obviously speaks in the more communal voice. Right, the basic שמונה עשרה
Shmoneh Esreh *Shemoneh Esrei* is all in the plural. אלקינו *Elokeinu*, right,
you know, רפאנו *Refaeinu*, etc. אשר בחרת בנו *Asher bacharta banu*. So
the private וידוי viduy *vidui* occurs after שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh *Shemoneh
Esrei*. ושליח ציבור אומרו באמצע *U'shliach tzibbur omro b'emtza*, the שליח ציבור
shaliach tzibur *shliach tzibbur* says it in the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh
*Shemoneh Esrei*. And that is about the character of the day and
it's also because there he is doing that represents the וידוי viduy,
*vidui* of the public and of the community, right? And that's the
whole idea why you do the וידוי viduy, *vidui* again in חזרת
הש"ץ *Chazaras Hashatz* because that's you're doing the וידוי viduy *vidui* as
part of the communal תשובה *teshuva* and the communal וידוי viduy. *vidui*
as opposed to the private one that you do after your שמונה
עשרה Shmoneh Esreh. *Shemoneh Esrei*. So מה אמר *mai amar*, what do
you say? How do you- how do you introduce the וידוי viduy
*vidui*? So אמר רב Rav אתה יודע רזי עולם *Amar Rav Ata
yodeia razei olam*, which is by the way how we introduce our
וידוי viduy *vidui*, if you remember I brought my מחזור *machzor*, right,
but the- the way you open up the וידוי viduy, *vidui* on
the, you know, after your שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh *Shemoneh Esrei*. By
the way while I'm looking for it I should say, there's a
whole question do you say it after you do יהיו לרצון אמרי
פי *yihyu l'ratzon imrei fi* or before יהיו לרצון אמרי פי *yihyu
l'ratzon imrei fi*? How much is it really when the שמונה עשרה
Shmoneh Esreh. *Shemoneh Esrei* is over? My practice, I think that the
most accepted practice is to start the וידוי viduy *vidui* before you
do the יהיו לרצון אמרי פי *yihyu l'ratzon imrei fi* because on
the one hand it's not part of the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh.
*Shemoneh Esrei* and on the other hand you want it like the
לפני ה' *lifnei Hashem*. The reason you do the וידוי viduy *vidui*
right after שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esreh. *Shemoneh Esrei* is as of doing
it directly in the presence of God. So that you wait to
do the יהיו לרצון *yihyu l'ratzon* which finally ends the שמונה עשרה
Shmoneh Esreh, *Shemoneh Esrei* and first you do the וידוי viduy *vidui*
and then you do יהיו לרצון *yihyu l'ratzon* as at least that's
the way that I do it. Anyway we introduce it, right, we
say
you know we say- well that's actually here the שליח ציבור shaliach
tzibur *shliach tzibbur*, let me get the individual שמונה עשרה *Shemoneh Esrei*,
right, so the way we do it is, right, you- so here
it has יהיו לרצון *yihyu l'ratzon* before the וידוי vidui. *vidui*. אלקינו
ואלקי אבותינו תבוא לפניך תפילתנו *Elokeinu v'Elokei avoseinu tavo lefanecha tefilasenu*, etc.,
etc. אשמנו בגדנו Ashamnu Bagadnu, *ashamnu bagadnu* and then it's אתה יודע
רזי עולם ופושע כל חפץ חי אתה חופש כל חדרי בטן *Ata
yodeia razei olam u'foseia kol chafetz chai Ata chofesh kol chadrei beten*
and then it gets into the על חטא *al cheit*. Okay, so
that's the intro he says אתה יודע רזי עולם *Ata yodeia razei
olam*. ושמואל אמר ממעמקי הלב *U'Shmuel amar mima'amakei halev*, Shmuel had some
different type of an introduction, from the depths of a heart of
the heart. ולוי אמר ובתורתך כתוב *V'Levi amar u'v'sorascha kasuv*,
which is quite fascinating, and רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it means כי
ביום הזה יכפר עליכם ki bayom hazeh yechaper aleichem. *ki bayom hazeh
yichaper aleichem*, which is what we say in the שמונה עשרה *Shemoneh
Esrei* itself as part of the ברכה bracha *bracha*. Quite a fascinating
way of introducing the וידוי vidui. *vidui* to saying that we're going
to be atoned rather than introducing
the. Master of the universe and then obviously they were referring to
different texts. Again, they don't even have to spell it out. They
clearly were different texts that they were aware of and that were
different options, and that's what they and they were each one referring
to a different way of introducing the, what do you call it,
the וידוי. vidui. רש"י Rashi says it's ריבון עולמים כי לא על
צדקותינו אנחנו מפילים
תחנוננו לפניך, Ribon Olamim Ki Lo Al Tzidkotenu Anachnu Mapilim Tachanunenu Lefanecha,
the text that we know that precedes a
תחנון. tachanun. רבי יהודה אומר Rabbi Yehuda Omer כי עוונותינו רבו מלמנות
וחטאותינו עצמו מספר, Ki Avonotenu Rabu Milimnot Vechat'otenu Atzmu Misaper, which is
also a text that we use, our sins are so great, etc.,
מספר. misaper. רב המנונא אומר Rav Hamnuna Omer אלוקי, Elokai, and this
is what we עד שלא נוצרתי איני כדאי, Ad Shelo Notzarti Eini
Kedai, before I was created I am not worthy, ועכשיו שנוצרתי כאילו
לא נוצרתי, Ve'achshav Shenotzarti Ke'ilu Lo Notzarti, now that I've been created
it's as if I wasn't created, עפר אני בחיי קל וחומר במיתתי,
Afar Ani Bechayai Kal Vachomer Bemitatati, I am like dust in my
life, certainly in my death, הרי אני לפניך ככלי מלא בושה וכלימה,
Harei Ani Lefanecha Kichli Malei Busha Uklima, behold I am like you
like a vessel filled with shame and
embarrassment, יהי רצון מלפניך שלא אחטא עוד ומה שחטאתי מרק ברחמיך, Yehi
Ratzon Milifanecha Shelo Echta Od Umah Shechatati Mareik Berachamecha, cleanse, again, there's
that idea of cleansing that יום כיפור Yom Kippur, and ייסורים yissurim
are cleansing, אבל לא על ידי ייסורים, Aval Lo Al Yedei Yissurim,
so that's an interesting if you read it in context of what
we said two days ago about the ייסורים yissurim are ממרקין, marmarkin,
are scour and cleanse, here he's saying God please cleanse me but
not with the ייסורים. yissurim. Okay, now by the way that is
what we say at the end of שמונה עשרה on יום כיפור
Yom Kippur before the normal
אלוקי, Elokai, we do the עד שלא נוצרתי Ad Shelo Notzarti and
then we get to אלוקי נצור לשוני מרע Elokai Netzor Leshoni Mera
and so on. So that actually is what we incorporate after the
וידוי. viduy. והיינו וידויה דרבא כולה שתא, Vehainu Viduyah Derava Kulei Shata,
that is the וידוי viduy, that רבא Rava would do the whole
year, not just on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Again, what's fascinating about
all of this is that they're talking about the liturgy that frames
the וידוי. viduy. They're not saying אשמנו בגדנו, Ashamnu Bagadnu על חטא
שחטאנו לפניך. Al Cheit Shechatanu Lefanecha. One imagines that that was taken
for granted, that there would be some actual וידוי that went on.
But again, the interesting quest, and they're not talking about just do
this, don't actually confess the sin, just say these general statements that
I sinned. But maybe not, before we learned a question about whether
you צריך לפרט את החטא. tzarich lefareit et hacheit. Is it possible
that they're suggesting that all you do by the וידוי is God
I sinned before you please forgive me? That would be a וידוי
if you don't have to be מפרט את החטא. mefareit et hacheit.
The alternative possibility why they're not discussing the אשמנו בגדנו Ashamnu Bagadnu,
and על חטא שחטאנו לפניך Al Cheit Shechatanu Lefanecha is maybe it's
like a fill in the blank here, meaning maybe they're talking about
the framing and what constitutes the actual וידוי, you work it out
yourself, that's the text that you're supposed to say. Okay, so again,
it's worth noting that they don't have what we would identify as
the עיקר וידוי. ikar viduy. They're talking about the framing. Was that
all they did, the framing? Or maybe they had a ritualized וידוי,
they didn't have to discuss it, or maybe you were supposed to
actually fill it in with your own confession. Okay,
where are we? דרב המנונא זוטא ביומא דכיפורי, Derav Hamnuna Zuta Beyoma
Dekippurei, and that was רב המנונא Rav Hamnuna the younger's וידוי on
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur this עד שלא נוצרתי. Ad Shelo Notzarti. אמר
מר זוטרא Amar Mar Zutra לא אמרן אלא דלא אמר אבל אנחנו
חטאנו. Lo Amran Ela Dela Amar Aval Anachnu Chatanu. All these issues
is only if you don't say אבל אנחנו חטאנו. Aval Anachnu Chatanu.
אבל אמר אבל אנחנו חטאנו, Aval Amar Aval Anachnu Chatanu, but we
have sinned, תו לא צריך, tu lo tzarich, those three words, you
don't have to do anything else. And presumably again, now he's not
talking about the framing of it, presumably the actual וידוי. If וידוי
you don't have to be מפרט
את החטא, mefareit et hacheit, the bottom line וידוי is we sinned.
Why say אבל אנחנו חטאנו, Aval Anachnu Chatanu, just say אנחנו חטאנו,
Anachnu Chatanu, say חטאתי, chatati, as again it's still interesting. But it
says, you know what, just saying you sinned, that's already doing it.
דאמר בר המדודי De'amar Bar Hamdudi הוה קאימנא קמיה דשמואל, Havah Ka'amina
Kamei Deshmuel, I was standing before שמואל, Shmuel, ויתיב, veyativ, and שמואל
Shmuel was sitting. וכי מטא שליחא דציבורא, Vchi Mata Shlicha Detzibbura, and
when the שליח ציבור came to the point אבל אנחנו חטאנו, Aval
Anachnu Chatanu, which is the words we say right before we do
the אשמנו בגדנו,
קם מקם, Kam Mikam, שמואל Shmuel stood up. שמע מינה עיקר וידוי
האי הוא, Shma Mina Ikar Viduy Hai Hu, this is the real
וידוי, that phrase אבל אנחנו חטאנו. Aval Anachnu Chatanu. Again, it's quite
fascinating. First of all, the assumption that because he stood indicates that
that's the עיקר וידוי, ikar viduy, some ראשונים rishonim have the גירסא
girsa not שמע מינה shma mina this is the וידוי but שמע
מינה shma mina that וידוי has to be done standing. That that's
the point that's actually being underscored by שמואל Shmuel standing up. Ah,
you see, when you do וידוי you have to stand. But again,
it's a fascinating phrase, so it means that A, clearly they had
the liturgy, a lot of the liturgy was that we are familiar
with or a lot of liturgy was already there, they're not spelling
it out for us, but when they said the שליח ציבור said
אבל אנחנו חטאנו Aval Anachnu Chatanu and שמואל Shmuel got up, was
it followed with the אשמנו בגדנו גזלנו דברנו דופי Ashamnu Bagadnu Gazalnu
Dibarnu Dofi or something like that, or no, that was it, just.
Believe me, what was his גרסא? girsa? He says תורת כהנים Torat
Kohanim more than what? What did he have before? Believe me, what
was his גרסא? girsa? What did he say? Rashi says it says,
you know, כי
ביום הזה יכפר עליכם. But again, that's not even a וידוי. Okay,
so quite fascinating these discussions and what isn't sort of being addressed
and whether we're talking about the framing or we're talking about the
actual substance of the וידוי. תנן התם, Tnan hatam, we taught over
there: שלושה פרקים בשנה כהנים נושאים את כפיהם ארבע פעמים ביום. Shlosha
perakim bashana kohanim nosim et kapeihem, arba pe'amim bayom. There's three times
in the year that כהנים kohanim do ברכת כהנים birkat kohanim for
four times in the day: בשחרית במוסף במנחה ובנעילת שערים. Beshacharit bemussaf
bemincha uvine'ilat she'arim. שחרית, Shacharit, מוסף, mussaf, מנחה, mincha, נעילה. ne'ila.
Which basically means that there are three times when you do נעילה,
ne'ila, and because those are fast days, a כהן doesn't do ברכת
כהנים birkat kohanim later in the afternoon because he might have been
drunk by then. But on a fast day, that's why you do
ברכת כהנים birkat kohanim at מנחה. mincha. So what it's really saying
is there are three times where you're fasting and therefore כהנים kohanim
do ברכת כהנים birkat kohanim the whole day, and where there's נעילה.
ne'ila. What are those times? ואלו הן שלושה פרקים תעניות, Ve'elu hen
shelosha perakim ta'aniyot, on the תענית, ta'anis, you know, that you do
for rain, so there would be a נעילה. ne'ila. ומעמדות, Vemamadot, which
would be the groups of the Jews that would gather to represent
the Jewish people in terms of the קרבנות korbanot that were being
brought,
and they would fast on particular days, וביום הכפורים, uveyom hakippurim, and
on Yom Kippur. So by the way, as Michael's indicating, on תענית
ta'anis and מעמדות mamadot there aren't מוסף, mussaf, so fine. מוסף Mussaf
was לאו דוקא, lav davka, but the point is you fast, you
have נעילה ne'ila and therefore the כהנים kohanim do ברכת כהנים birkat
kohanim the whole day. So every time. Now the גמרא Gemara says:
מאי נעילת שערים? mai ne'ilat she'arim?
What do you do for the locking of the gates? By the
way, what locked gates are being locked? Rashi brings down a ירושלמי
Yerushalmi that some have that it's with the locking of the gates
of heaven, which is how we daven, and some say it means
the opposite, the locking of the gates of the עזרה, Azara, which
is just a way of referring to the very last moment of
the day. One still though imagines locking of the gates of עזרה
Azara is, you know, symbolically communicating the same idea as the locking
of the gates of heaven. Okay, so fine. So what was the
locking... what was the locking... I'm sorry, what do you say for
נעילה? ne'ila? רב אמר צלותא יתירתא, Rav amar: tzeluta yetira, you do
another שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. ושמואל אמר מה אנו מה חיינו. Ushmuel
amar: mah anu mah chayeinu. No, you don't do another שמנה עשרה.
Shemoneh Esrei. It's just another like a supplication. What are we? How,
you know, what's the value of our lives? Some type of סליחה,
selicha, but you don't do another שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. Okay, which
is funny. How do you do a ברכת כהנים birkat kohanim not
in the context of שמנה עשרה? Shemoneh Esrei? Anyway, מיתיבי, meitivei, I'll
ask you, or I mean you could, but that's not the normal
standard. או יום הכפורים מתפלל שבע ומתוודה בשחרית. Or Yom hakippurim mitpalel
sheva umitvadeh beshacharit. On, you know, like Kol Nidre night, you do
a
שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei with seven ברכות brachot and you do וידוי.
בשחרית מתפלל שבע ומתוודה, Beshacharit mitpalel sheva umitvadeh, you do it in
שחרית. Shacharit. במוסף מתפלל שבע ומתוודה, Bemussaf mitpalel sheva umitvadeh, במנחה מתפלל
שבע ומתוודה, bemincha mitpalel sheva umitvadeh, בנעילה מתפלל שבע ומתוודה. bine'ila mitpalel
sheva umitvadeh. In נעילה ne'ila you do it and in the morning,
so you say you do a seven-ברכה bracha שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei.
So you see נעילה ne'ila is a שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. And
then now people take out the word תניא tanya because it's another...
another ברייתא baraita reinforces this. Some say ותניא: v'o tanya: יום הכפורים
עם חשיכה מתפלל שבע ומתוודה, Yom hakippurim im chashecha mitpalel sheva umitvadeh,
וחותם בוידוי. vechoteim bevidui. That the חתימה chatima that you do on
נעילה ne'ila according to this, דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir, according
to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, is not the normal חתימה chatima about
מקדש ישראל ויום הכפורים, mekadesh Yisrael veyom hakippurim, but it's a חתימה
chatima about like שאתה סולחן לישראל, she'atah solchan leyisrael, which is funny.
The word is חותם בוידוי, choteim bevidui, which is your confession. But
Rashi, when he suggests what the text would be, Rashi says that
the חתימה chatima would be you forgive Israel. What's Rashi, hold on.
וחותם בוידוי, Vechoteim bevidui, Rashi says,
האל
הסולחן,
ha-Eil
ha-solechan, the forgiving God. So again, the identification of confession
and forgiveness, right? Is not, you know, again like the point I
was making before, the way you bring out the theme of Yom
Kippur as a day of forgiveness is you do a confession at
every שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. So to say that if Rashi is
correct that the חתימה chatima would be God who forgives Israel and
we're describing it as חותם בוידוי, choteim bevidui, right? That's not a
confession, God who forgives Israel. That's God forgiving us. So again, that
strong identification of the two is worth noting. Anyway, so this says
that the חתימה chatima of the שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei of נעילה
ne'ila is that of forgiveness according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. וחכמים
אומרים מתפלל שבע ואם רצה לחתום בוידוי חותם. Vachachamim omrim: mitpalel sheva
ve'im ratzah lachtom bevidui choteim. If you want, you could end with
the חתימה chatima of forgiveness, if otherwise you could end with the
standard חתימה chatima of, you know, מקדש ישראל ויום הכפורים. mekadesh Yisrael
veyom hakippurim. It should be worth noting that the ברכה bracha, of
Yom Kippur, the last ברכה, bracha the middle ברכה bracha of שמנה
עשרה Shemoneh Esrei is quite a long one and is very much,
you know, has the theme of forgiveness, right?
כי אתה סולחן לישראל. Ki atah solchan leyisrael. I mean, where do
we ever have a חתימה chatima of a ברכה bracha that long?
Okay, but it is exactly doing this of intertwining the normal middle
ברכה bracha of מקדש ישראל mekadesh yisrael the X, ויום הכפורים, veyom
hakippurim, plus that whole character of the day of forgiveness, which the
גמרא Gemara here is calling חותם בוידוי. choteim be-viduy. Anyway, as far
as our issue, that you see that נעילה Ne'ilah is a שמונה
עשרה, so the גמרא Gemara says תיובתא דשמואל תיובתא. tiyuvta de-Shmuel tiyuvta.
Fine, that's the contradiction against שמואל. Shmuel. You see that נעילה Ne'ilah
is a שמונה עשרה. בא... Ba... okay, עולא בר
רב נחית קמיה דרבה. Ulla bar Rav nachit kamei de-Rabbah. Son of
רב Rav went in front of רבה Rabba to lead the דאוונינג.
davening. עולא בר רב? Ulla bar Rav? What? עולא בר רב. Ulla
bar Rav. No, I'm sorry, thank you. עולא בר רב, Ulla bar
Rav, thank you. עולא בר רב נחית קמיה דרבה. Ulla bar Rav
nachit kamei de-Rabbah. פתח באתה בחרתנו Patach be-Atah Vechartanu וסיים במה אנו
מה חיינו. ve-siyem be-Ma Anu Ma Chayeinu. So he began the middle
ברכה bracha of שמונה עשרה with אתה בחרתנו, Atah Vechartanu, which is
how we begin it, and he ended it with מה אנו מה
חיינו Ma Anu Ma Chayeinu like with the whole theme of וידוי.
ושבחיה רבה, Ve-shabchei Rabbah, and רבה Rabbah praised him. Okay, רבה לטעמיה
דאמר... Rabbah le-ta'ameih de-amar... did I skip a line? Yes, I did.
הונא בריה דרב נתן... Huna berei de-Rav Natan...
ושבחיה. ve-shabchei.
Thank you. I don't know, I'm even trying to go too fast,
because this was in front of רבה, Rabba, right, and he praised
him. רב הונא בריה דרב נתן אמר: Rav Huna berei de-Rav Natan
amar: ויחיד אומר אחר תפלתו. Veyachid omer achar tfillato. An individual says
the מה אנו מה חיינו Ma Anu Ma Chayeinu not in the
middle of the שמונה עשרה but after the שמונה עשרה. Same like
the whole idea before about saying וידוי, same with this particular prayer.
אמר רב: תפלת נעילה פוטרת של ערבית. Amar Rav: Tfillat Ne'ilah poteret
shel Arvit. When you דאוון נעילה, daven Ne'ilah,
you don't have to דאוון מעריב daven Maariv because presumably because as
we're going to see, according to him you could דאוון נעילה daven
Ne'ilah after it's already night. So you're doing a שמונה עשרה and
it's already night. Of course your שמונה עשרה has only seven ברכות
brachot and it's a whole יום כפור Yom Kippur theme, but nevertheless,
it's a שמונה עשרה at night that gets you off the hook
for דאוונינג מעריב. davening Maariv. So רב לטעמיה, Rav le-ta'ameih, רב goes
according to his reasons, דאמר צלותא יתירתא היא, de-amar tzlota yetirta hi,
that it's another שמונה עשרה. וכיון דצלי לה, Ve-keivan de-tzali lah, and
since you've done another שמונה עשרה at night, תו לא צריך, tu
lo tzarich, you don't have to דאוון מעריב daven Maariv again. So
the גמרא Gemara says: ומי אמר רב הכי? U-mi amar Rav hachi?
Did רב say this? והאמר רב: הלכה כדברי האומר תפלת ערבית רשות.
Ve-ha-amar Rav: halacha ke-divrei ha-omer tfillat Arvit reshut. That מעריב Maariv is
just a רשות. reshut. And therefore why do you have to say
that you're exempt from מעריב Maariv anyway, you don't have to דאוון
daven it, which leads תוספות Tosafot in a whole discussion that even
if we say מעריב Maariv is a רשות, reshut, does it really
mean you don't have to do it? But anyway, that's the way
the גמרא Gemara is sounding. If מעריב Maariv is only a רשות,
reshut, you didn't have to do it anyway. So what do you
mean it exempted you?
So the גמרא Gemara says no: לדברי האומר חובה קאמר. Le-divrei ha-omer
chova ka'amar. No, he means even those who say מעריב Maariv is
an obligation, נעילה Ne'ilah is מוציא motzi you. מיתיבי: Meitivei: Is this
really true?
אור יום הכפורים מתפלל שבע ומתוודה. Or Yom HaKippurim mitpalel sheva u-mitvadeh.
שחרית שבע ומתוודה. Shacharit sheva u-mitvadeh. מוסף שבע ומתוודה. Musaf sheva u-mitvadeh.
בנעילה מתפלל שבע ומתוודה. Be-Ne'ilah mitpalel sheva u-mitvadeh. So the ברייתא braita
we heard before that at each one of the דאוונינגס davenings you
say seven ברכות brachot and a וידוי. But then it goes on
to say: במנחה מתפלל שבע ומתוודה... Be-Mincha mitpalel sheva u-mitvadeh... is missing
anyway. ערבית מתפלל שבע מעין שמונה עשרה. Arvit mitpalel sheva mei'ein Shmoneh
Esreh. And מעריב Maariv after it just said you דאוון נעילה, daven
Ne'ilah, it says and you're going to דאוון מעריב. daven Maariv. What
do you do by מעריב? Maariv? So there, you don't have to
do the whole שמונה עשרה. You've been fasting a whole day. Do
a short שמונה עשרה. So the middle one, right, says there הביננו.
Havineinu. There's a way you can do a summary of the eighteen
ברכות brachot in one ברכה bracha in the middle, which they established
as a נוסח nusach for somebody who's traveling and who can't focus
on the שמונה עשרה. So do that מוצאי יום כפור. Motzaei Yom
Kippur. We'll make it easy for you. Do seven, but the middle
one will be a distillation of the eighteen ברכות. brachot. Okay, right.
רבי חנינא בן גמליאל משום אבותיו מתפלל שמונה עשרה שלמות. Rabbi Chanina
ben Gamliel mishum avotav mitpalel Shmoneh Esreh shelemot. No, you do a
full eighteen. Why? מפני שצריך לומר הבדלה בחונן הדעת. mipnei she-tzarich lomar
havdalah be-Chonein HaDa'at. Because you've got to say הבדלה. havdalah. So sorry,
you can't get a... So oh, it was so good! We could
have got away with a little שמונה עשרה, you know, מוצאי יום
כפור. Motzaei Yom Kippur. But now because we have to say הבדלה,
havdalah, we gotta say... yeah, because you can't do a הבדלה havdalah
without doing each ברכה bracha by... without doing each ברכה by itself.
By the way, I should say תוספות Tosafot says the reason of
the first opinion was not just to make life easy for you,
but he says since you haven't yet broken the fast, to some
degree you're still in the יום כפור Yom Kippur mode and therefore
we want to get you to say another יום כפור-like Yom Kippur
דאוונינג, davening, so we want to have seven ברכות brachot like the
יום כפור Yom Kippur דאוונינג davening had seven ברכות. brachot. So it
wasn't just to be easy for you. Anyway, we פסקן pasken the
second opinion that we do a full דאוונינג davening so you can
say הבדלה. havdalah. Anyway, what do you see? You see that even
though
you did נעילה, Ne'ilah, you still have to do מעריב. Maariv. So
the גמרא Gemara says: תנאי היא. Tanna'ei hi. It's a debate of
תנאים. Tannaim. דתניא, De-tanya, it was taught in a ברייתא: braita: כל
חייבי טבילות טובלים כדרכם ביום הכפורים. Kol chayevei tevilot tovlin ke-darkam be-Yom
HaKippurim. Anybody who has to go to the מקוה mikvah is allowed
to go on יום כפור Yom Kippur because it's not a טבילה
tevila for תענוג. ta'anug. נדה ויולדת טובלת כדרכה בליל יום הכפורים. Niddah
ve-yoledet tovelet ke-darkah be-leil Yom HaKippurim. A נדה niddah and יולדת yoledet
can go on, you
know, כל נדרי Kol Nidrei night, again, because it's not for תענוג
ta'anug purposes, it's for מקוה mikvah purposes. בעל קרי טובל והולך עד
המנחה. Ba'al keri tovel ve-holech ad ha-Mincha. A בעל קרי ba'al keri
who can't דאוון daven until he's gone to the מקוה, mikvah, because
of the תקנה takkanah that a בעל קרי ba'al keri can't דאוון,
daven, which we don't פסקן pasken anymore, so he goes or maybe
must go, not just is allowed to go, until מנחה Mincha time.
But once he's דאוונד... davened... מנחה Mincha and then he became a
בעל קרי, Baal Keri, then there's no need to go anymore because
there's no דאווענינג Davening left to be done. So, meaning, well what
about נעילה? Neilah? So implicit in this is נעילה Neilah is at
night. And therefore you don't go on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur you
don't have to go today on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur wait till
night, go at night and then דאווען Daven נעילה. Neilah.
So, רבי יוסי אומר כל היום כולו. Rabbi Yosi Omer Kol HaYom
Kulo. No, he goes to the מקוה Mikvah again even after מנחה
Mincha in order to allow him to דאווען Daven נעילה. Neilah. So
the way the גמרא Gemara is understanding it is where you have
an implicit debate here whether נעילה Neilah is before nightfall or after
nightfall, because if it's after nightfall the בעל קרי Baal Keri doesn't
have to go to the מקוה Mikvah during יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
and if it's after, the only possibility that you're מוציא Motzi מעריב
Maariv by נעילה Neilah is if it is after nightfall. So nobody's
dealing with the bizarre nature that a יום כיפור Yom Kippur. דאווענינג
Davening is going to be מוציא Motzi you from מעריב. Maariv. But
the only issue is did you do it at nightfall? So the
גמרא Gemara says look, there's an implicit debate here whether נעילה Neilah
is during the day or once it's night. That would be the
issue about whether you're מוציא Motzi מעריב. Maariv. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says רמינהי Raminihi I'll ask you on this: הזב והזבה והמצורע
והמצורעת ובועל נדה וטמאי מת טובלין כדרכן ביום הכיפורים, HaZav vehaZava vehaMetzora
vehaMetzora'at uboel Nidda utmei meit tovlin kedarkam beYom HaKippurim, all these טמאי
tmei people can go to the מקוה Mikvah on יום כיפור. Yom
Kippur. נדה ויולדת טובלין כדרכן בליל יום הכיפורים. Nidda veYoledet tovlin kedarkam
beLeil Yom HaKippurim. בעל קרי טובל והולך כל היום כולו Baal Keri
tovel veholech kol hayom kulo and the בעל קרי Baal Keri can
go the whole day of יום כיפור Yom Kippur, because he's got
to דאווען. Daven. רבי יוסי אומר מן המנחה ולמעלה אין יכול לטבול.
Rabbi Yosi omer mina hamincha ulema'ala ein yachol litbol. Only from מנחה
Mincha time he can't, so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi reversed his position.
Before רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi said you could go after מנחה Mincha
because you have to say נעילה. Neilah. גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא,
Lo kashya, it's not difficult.
הא דצלי תפילת נעילה הא דלא צלי. Ha de'tzali tfilas Neilah ha
de'lo tzali. The difference is whether you've דאווענט Davened נעילה. Neilah. If
you've already דאווענט Davened נעילה Neilah you can't or you don't have
to go. After you've דאווענט, Davened, if you haven't דאווענט Davened נעילה
Neilah you can, but רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi is still on his
position that נעילה Neilah is during the day. So גמרא Gemara says
אי דצלי, I de'tzali, if you've already said נעילה, Neilah, מאי טעמא
דרבנן? mai ta'ama d'Rabbanan? Why do the רבנן Rabbanan let the בעל
קרי Baal Keri go or demand that the בעל קרי Baal Keri
go after נעילה Neilah in this second ברייתא? Baraita? That the רבנן
Rabbanan are saying you go the whole day? Why if you've already
דאווענט? Davened? So גמרא Gemara says קסברי רבנן טבילה בזמנה מצוה. kasavri
Rabbanan tevilah bizmanah mitzvah. The רבנן Rabbanan say טבילה בזמנה מצוה. tevilah
bizmanah mitzvah. It doesn't matter about whether you need to go to
the מקוה Mikvah in order to דאווען. Daven. There's a מצוה mitzvah
to go on the right time. So if you became a בעל
קרי Baal Keri today you've got to go today even if you've
done all of your דאווענינג Davening and that's why they say it.
So גמרא says מכלל דרבי יוסי סבר לאו מצוה היא? mikal d'Rabbi
Yosi savar lav mitzvah hi? So that suggesting that רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi who says he doesn't go if he's already done all of
his דאווענינג, Davening, the בעל קרי, Baal Keri, says it's not a
מצוה mitzvah to go on the right time? והתניא, Veha Tanya, we
learned in a ברייתא, Baraita, הרי שהיה שם כתוב על בשרו. harei
shehaya shem katuv al besaro. Somebody wrote God's name on his arm.
Okay, הרי זה לא ירחץ, harei zeh lo yirchatz, he can't bathe,
ולא יסוך, velo yasuch, and put oil, ולא יעמוד במקום הטינופת, velo
ya'amod bemakom hatinofet, or stand in a place of filth because it's
inappropriate for God's name, and the other part would be erasing God's
name. נזדמנה לו טבילת מצוה, Nizdamna lo tevilat mitzvah, let's say you
have to go to the מקוה, Mikvah, כורך עליו גמי, korech alav
gemi, put a band around it, ויורד וטובל כדרכו, veyored vetovel kedarko,
and go to the מקוה, Mikvah, so it won't necessarily, it's loose
enough that water can get in, it's a good טבילה, tevilah, but
it's enough protecting it that it won't necessarily erase God's name. רבי
יוסי אומר יורד וטובל כדרכו ובלבד שלא ישפשף. Rabbi Yosi omer yored
vetovel kedarko uvelvad shelo yeshashaf. No,
you don't have to put a band around it, go straight into
the מקוה, Mikvah, just don't rub it when you're in the water.
Okay, וקיימא לן, veka'imlan, what's that a debate about? So we have
established דטבילה בזמנה מצוה פליגי. de'tevilah bizmanah mitzvah pligi.
The debate is whether going to the מקוה Mikvah on its right
time is a מצוה. mitzvah. How is that a debate? Because גמרא
says what's the problem of saying put a band around God's name,
protect God's name? No, the reason רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi wouldn't want
you to do it is because that will delay you from going
to the מקוה Mikvah on the right time. You won't find a
good bandage to put on it, and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi wants
to ensure you go to the מקוה Mikvah on the right time.
Okay, so that debate is framed as whether טבילה בזמנה מצוה. tevilah
bizmanah mitzvah. So you see רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says טבילה בזמנה
tevilah bizmanah is a מצוה. mitzvah. So how is he saying in
the ברייתא Baraita don't go on יום כיפור Yom Kippur, if you
became a בעל קרי Baal Keri after you דאווענט Davened נעילה? Neilah?
Who cares if you've דאווענט Davened נעילה Neilah already? רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi is the one that says טבילה בזמנה tevilah bizmanah is a
מצוה. mitzvah. So the גמרא says
no, הא רבי יוסי בר יהודה היא.
ha Rabbi
Yosi bar Yehuda hi.
That idea that טבילה בזמנה tevilah bizmanah is not a מצוה mitzvah
and that you don't go to the מקוה Mikvah if you're a
בעל קרי Baal Keri after נעילה Neilah is רבי יוסי בר יהודה.
Rabbi Yosi bar Yehuda. דתניא De'Tanya רבי יוסי בר יהודה אומר די
לה לטבילה שתהא באחרונה. Rabbi Yosi bar Yehuda omer dai la litevilah
shetehei ba'acharona. There's a famous case about a woman who comes and
says I don't know when I became a נדה, Nidda, and basically
in the גמרא they have her go to the מקוה Mikvah like
sixty times because you want to make sure you're getting the exact
right day that it's your מצוה mitzvah to go to the מקוה.
Mikvah. And רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says give me a break, just
go on the last day and then she's definitely טהורה, tehora, which
means there's no idea of going on the exact right day. Do
a מקוה Mikvah at the end and make her טהורה. tehora. So
that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi is the one that holds טבילה בזמנה
tevilah bizmanah is not a מצוה. mitzvah. We did that very quickly,
but again the upshot is are you מוציא Motzi מעריב Maariv by
נעילה Neilah if נעילה Neilah is at night, which is again bizarre.
If נעילה Neilah is at night, there's a debate whether נעילה Neilah
is at night, which partly is seen through the lens of: Can
a בעל קרי Baal Keri go to the מקוה Mikvah on the
day in order to דאווען Daven נעילה? Neilah? So if נעילה Neilah
is in the day the answer is yes, but if נעילה Neilah
is at night, no he can't go because just Wait until the
night. And other questions about insisting that somebody go to the מקוה
mikvah on יום כיפור Yom Kippur even if they don't need to
go, even if they've דאוונט, davened, because of טבילה בזמנה מצוה. tevilah
bizmanah mitzvah. Let's just end. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: הרואה קרי ביום
הכיפורים, haro'eh keri b'Yom HaKippurim, if somebody actually becomes a בעל קרי
baal keri on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur. יורד וטובל ולערב ישפשף, yored
v'tovel u'l'erev yeshafshef, go down to the מקוה mikvah and scrub yourself
in the evening in order to make sure there are no חציצה.
chatzitzah. So הגמרא haGemara says ולערב? u'l'erev? מאי דהוה הוה. mai d'hava
hava. What could it do to remove חציצות chatzitzot after you've been
to the מקוה? mikvah? What was, was. אלא אימא מערב ישפשף, ella
eima me'erev yeshafshef,
scrub yourself on ערב יום כיפור erev Yom Kippur so you can
go to the מקוה mikvah on יום כיפור. Of course question is,
but I only became a בעל קרי baal keri on יום כיפור.
So רש"י Rashi says everybody has to scrub themselves on ערב erev
יום כיפור because they might become a בעל קרי baal keri on
יום כיפור, which gets back to the whole theme of like you
always have to be worried that something is about to go wrong.
And now just really to end it, תני תנא קמיה דרב נחמן:
tani tana kamei d'Rav Nachman: הרואה קרי ביום הכיפורים עונותיו מחולים לו.
haro'eh keri b'Yom HaKippurim avonotav mechulim lo. Again, like the irony before
about being suspended from a palm tree. If you see קרי keri
on יום כיפור, your sins are forgiven. והתניא עונותיו סדורין? vehatanya avonotav
sedurin?
Your sins are laid out for you. You're going to get punished
for all your sins. מאי סדורין סדורין לימחל. mai sedurin sedurin limachal.
No, it means laid out to be forgiven. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל:
tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael: הרואה קרי ביום הכיפורים ידאג כל השנה כולה.
haro'eh keri b'Yom HaKippurim yidag kol hashanah kulah. You should be worried
the whole year that you're going to be punished because it's a
terrible thing to become a בעל קרי baal keri on יום כיפור
and everybody else was restraining from sex and you were having this
thing which was sexually satisfying. So is that the bad sign? ואם
עלתה לו שנה, v'im altah lo shanah, but if you lived out
the year, מובטח לו שהוא בן עולם הבא. muvtach lo shehu ben
olam habah. Then you know it was a good sign, that God
wanted to give you a nice thing to give you this satisfaction
on
יום כיפור. אמר, that's the way רש"י Rashi says it. That's what
רש"י Rashi says. אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק: amar Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak: תדע, tedah, you should know, שכל העולם כולו רעב, shekol haolam
kulo ra'ev, everybody else is hungry, והוא שבע, v'hu saveia, you got
this sexual satisfaction. כי אתא רב דימי אמר: ki ata Rav Dimi
amar: מפיש חיי סגי ומסגי. mapish chayei sagi u'masgi. You have a
lot of life and you shall be have many children.
רש"י and תוספות Tosafot quote
the פסוק: pasuk: יראה זרע יאריך ימים. yireh zera yaarich yamim.
So again, I just find it
interesting.
הדרן עלך יום הכיפורים, hadran alach Yom HaKippurim, סליק
מסכת יומא.
selik Masechet Yoma.
Interesting to
note, interesting to note
the irony of the fact that you know the whole, well I'll
just
end it.
We have to
go.
I'll tell you the irony tomorrow.
All right, let's go. Somebody want to do the הדרן? hadran? Joey,
you want to say קדיש? Kaddish? Let's do the whole הדרן. hadran.
Next מסכת is סוכה. Sukkah. Everyone's invited. How are we supposed to
start
learning סוכה Sukkah right now? We are supposed to get out of
this room because we are delaying this class.